Guide to the Gianni Bertini Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gianni Bertini papers
1946-2010
GEN MSS 970
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
53.67
(100 boxes) + 15 broadside and 2 broadside oversize
The collection consists of scrapbooks, correspondence, photographs, posters, visual poetry, artwork, writings, audiovisual materials, and electronic media documenting the life and work of Gianni Bertini. Correspondence includes letters from artists, galleries, and others. Notable correspondents include P. A. Benoit, Jean-François Bory, Henri Chopin, Jacqueline de Jong, Jean Dubuffet, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Sarenco, and Serge Vandercam. Artwork includes examples of MEC-Art (mechanical artwork), paintings, and other works by Bertini, P. A. Benoit, Henri Chopin, Bernard Heidsieck, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Ben Vautier, and others.
Bertini, Gianni, 1922-2010
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: July 2012 Acquisition; August 2012 Acquisition; September 2013 Acquisitions; and January 2016 Acquisition.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Box 110 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 117 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
July 2012 Acquisition: Purchased from John Benjamins Antiquariat b.v. and Phillipe Luiggi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
August 2012 Acquisition: Purchased from Derbylius Libreria Galleria di Carla Roncato on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
September 2013 Acquisitions: Purchased from John Benjamins Antiquariat b.v. and Phillipe Luiggi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
January 2016 Acquisition: Purchased from Philippe Luigi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
Gianni Bertini
Gianni Bertini (1922-2010) was an Italian artist and visual poet.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of scrapbooks, correspondence, photographs, posters, visual poetry, artwork, writings, audiovisual materials, and electronic media documenting the life and work of Gianni Bertini. Correspondence includes letters from artists, galleries, and others. Notable correspondents include P. A. Benoit, Jean-François Bory, Henri Chopin, Jacqueline de Jong, Jean Dubuffet, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Sarenco, and Serge Vandercam. Artwork includes examples of MEC-Art (mechanical artwork), paintings, and other works by Bertini, P. A. Benoit, Henri Chopin, Bernard Heidsieck, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Ben Vautier, and others.
Artists -- Italy; Visual poetry, Italian -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Photographs; Posters; Visual poetry; Artists -- Italy -- 20th Century; Benoit, P. A. (Pierre André); Bertini, Gianni, 1922-2010; Bory, Jean-François, 1938-; Chopin, Henri, 1922-2008; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-1985; Heidsieck, Bernard, 1928-2014; Jong, Jacqueline de, 1939-; Lambert, Jean-Clarence, 1930-; Sarenco, 1945-; Vandercam, Serge; Vautier, Ben, 1935-
- July 2012 Acquisition, 1946-2010; 46.67; (93 boxes) + 15 broadside and 2 oversize broadside
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from John Benjamins Antiquariat b.v. and Phillipe Luiggi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
  Arrangement
  Organized into eight series: Scrapbooks, 1946-2007; Correspondence, 1947-2010; Photographs, undated; Posters, 1954-1980; MEC-Art, 1970s-2000s; Visual poetry, 1961-1965; Artwork, 1951-2006; Electronic media, undated.
  - Scrapbooks, 1946-2007
    Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically.
    - Scrapbook, 1946-1956 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Scrapbook, 1969 (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1972 (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook, 1973 (Box 13)
    - Scrapbook, 1974 (Box 14)
    - Scrapbook, 1975-1976 (Box 15)
    - Scrapbook, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Scrapbook, 1980 (Box 18)
    - Scrapbook, 1981 (Box 19)
    - Scrapbook, 1982-1983 (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Scrapbook, 1985-1987 (Box 22)
    - Scrapbook, 1988 (Box 23)
    - Scrapbook, 1989 (Box 24)
    - Scrapbook [Part 1 of 2], 1990 (Box 25)
    - Scrapbook [Part 2 of 2], 1990 (Box 26)
    - Scrapbook [Part 1 of 2], 1991 (Box 27)
    - Scrapbook [Part 2 of 2], 1991 (Box 28)
    - Scrapbook, 1992 (Box 29)
    - Scrapbook, 1993 (Box 30)
    - Scrapbook, 1994 (Box 31)
    - Scrapbook, 1995-1996 (Box 32)
    - Scrapbook, 1997-1998 (Box 33)
    - Scrapbook, 1999 (Box 34)
    - Scrapbook, 2000-2003 (Box 35)
    - Scrapbook, 2004-2005 (Box 36)
    - Scrapbook, 2006-2007 (Box 37)
  - Correspondence, 1947-2010
    The bulk of the correspondence is organized chronologically. Some correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name, and correspondence with publisher P. A. Benoit (PAB) was not integrated into the primary chronological sequence.
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence includes letters from artists, galleries, and others. Transcribed correspondence includes both originals and transcriptions. Notable correspondents include P. A. Benoit (PAB), Jean-François Bory, Henri Chopin, Jacqueline de Jong, Jean Dubuffet, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Sarenco, and Serge Vandercam.
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 38)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1949 (Box 39)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1950 (Box 40)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1951 (Box 41)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1952 (Box 42)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1953 (Box 43)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1954 (Box 44)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 45)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1958 (Box 46)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1959 (Box 47)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1960 (Box 48)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1961 (Box 49)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 50)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1964 (Box 51)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1965 (Box 52)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1966 (Box 53)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1967 (Box 54)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1968 (Box 55)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1969 (Box 56)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1970 (Box 57)
    - Transcribed correspondence, 1971 (Box 58)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1972 (Box 59)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1973 (Box 60)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1974 (Box 61)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1975 (Box 62)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1976 (Box 63)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1977 (Box 64)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1978 (Box 65)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1979 (Box 66)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1980 (Box 67)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1981 (Box 68)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 69)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1976-1987 (Box 70)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1988-1994 (Box 71)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 72)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 73)
    - Untranscribed correspondence, 2002-2010 (Box 74)
    - Correspondence by name, 1994-1997 (Box 75)
    - P. A. Benoit (PAB) correspondence, 1960s-1980s (Box 76)
  - Photographs, undated
    - Photographs, undated (Box 77 (Oversize))
    - Photographs, undated (Box 78 (Oversize))
  - Posters, 1954-1980
    - de Filippi alla Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1965 (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Turi Simeti, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1969 (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Elio Mariani, Studio san Andrea, Milano, 1969 (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Ricerche 1969, Galleria d'arte "Il Brandale" Savona, Galleria d'arte "S. Gerolamo," Millesimo (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Franco Meneguzzo, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1968 (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Vargel Naumovski, Galleria de "il giorno," Milano, 1968 (Box 79 (Broadside))
    - Iro Novak, Galleria "il traghetto 1," Venezia, 1975 (Box 80 (Broadside))
    - Baj, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1968 (Box 80 (Broadside))
    - Degani, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1968 (Box 80 (Broadside))
    - Parisot, Galleria d'arte Luna 2, Torino, 1967 (Box 80 (Broadside))
    - Pistoletto, Galerie Sonnabend, Paris, 1967 (Box 81 (Broadside))
    - Harloff, Waddell, New York, 1972 (Box 81 (Broadside))
    - Simonetti, Galerie Apollinaire, Milano, 1972 (Box 81 (Broadside))
    - Ercole Pignateli, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1966 (Box 81 (Broadside))
    - Sangregorio, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1966 (Box 82 (Broadside))
    - Manifeste "il momento della verita," Galleria Apollinaire di Guido le Nocci, Milano, 1967 (Box 82 (Broadside))
    - Raynaud, Galleria Apollinaire, Milano, 1967 (Box 82 (Broadside))
    - Jiri Kolar, signé et daté 74, 1974 (Box 82 (Broadside))
    - Mondino, studio Marconi, Milano, 1967 (Box 83 (Oversize broadside))
    - FIU [Free International University]: discussione con Beuys, Pescara, 1978 (Box 84 (Broadside))
    - FIU: même expo mais poster différent, 1978 (Box 84 (Broadside))
    - Cioni Carpi - unde?, Torino, 1979 (Box 84 (Broadside))
    - Post no bills, segnali urbani, centro internazionale de Bera, Milano, 1979 (Box 84 (Broadside))
    - Erro, Galerie Nina Dausset, Paris, 1980 (Box 85 (Broadside))
    - Enrico Baj, Stufidre, Torino, 1980 (Box 85 (Broadside))
    - François Morelet, Studio Marconi, Milano, 1975 (Box 85 (Broadside))
    - Manifest "Les 2 realta" para Antonio Fomez, centro internazionale di ricerche e d'arte, Lerici, 1969-1980 (Box 85 (Broadside))
    - Zero, avant-garde, Galleria associazione Zen, Brescia, 1966 (Box 86 (Broadside))
    - Roberto Crippa, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1969 (Box 86 (Broadside))
    - Volpini, Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1967 (Box 86 (Broadside))
    - Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1966 (Box 86 (Broadside))
    - Pittura Oggettuale, Galleria associazione Zen,, Brescia, 1966 (Box 87 (Broadside))
    - Le scuplteur Fautrier, Galleria Apollinaire, Milano, 1966 (Box 87 (Broadside))
    - Moriconi, Galleria associazione Zen, Brescia, 1966 (Box 87 (Broadside))
    - Winfred Gaul: Arco d/Alibert, Roma, 1969 (Box 87 (Broadside))
    - Marco Gastini, Salone annunciata, Milano, 1969 (Box 88 (Broadside))
    - Fateve un rittratto stroboscopico, Galleria Solaria, Milano, 1969 (Box 88 (Broadside))
    - "Cartella 70" (texte de Dorfles, photo de Bueno, Loffredo, Armoretti, graphies musicales de Bussotti & Chiari, poésies visuelles de Miccini et Pignotti), Galleria studio G30, Paris, 1967? (Box 88 (Broadside))
    - L'asterisco dimestries tension 68, galerie l'Atelier, Toulouse, 1968 (Box 88 (Broadside))
    - Baj: Le dame di casa, textes d'Alain Jouffroy, studio Marconi, Milano, 1975 (Box 89 (Broadside))
    - Baj, studio Marconi, Milano, 1975 (Box 89 (Broadside))
    - Arakawa, Galleria associazione Zen, Brescia, 1967 (Box 89 (Broadside))
    - Elio Marchegiani, Galleria Apollinaire, Milano, 1966 (Box 89 (Broadside))
    - Hsiao Chin, Galleria il Canale, Venezia, 1966 (Box 89 (Broadside))
    - del Pezzo, d'Orgeix, Dova, Fontana, Licini, Magritte, Mathieu, Manzoni, Picabia, Pomodoro (A&G), Galleria Stefanoni, Lecco, 1966 (Box 90 (Broadside))
    - Manifeste P. Restany: cronica del XXI secolo di contenotte, Galleria Apollinaire, Milano, 1967 (Box 90 (Broadside))
    - Alex Mlynarcik: "Mégalithes du XXI s," Chatillon des arts, parc municipal, 1968 (Box 90 (Broadside))
    - Sebastiano de Laurentis, arco d'Alibert, Roma, 1969 (Box 90 (Broadside))
    - Piacentino, Galleria Toselli, Milano, 1969 (Box 91 (Broadside))
    - Multibox, centro ricerche estetiche f/uno, 1954 (Box 91 (Broadside))
    - Robert Cyprich & Alex Mlynarcik: "les jardins de contemplation," Bratislava, Tchecoslovaquie, 1970 (Box 91 (Broadside))
    - Bengston - Goode - Graham - Moses - Price - Ruscha: "Graphics," Galleria Milano, Milano, 1970 (Box 91 (Broadside))
    - Alic Cavaliere: "de Filippi cavaliere siete un unico pompiere," protesta studenti di Brera, Milano, 1971? (Box 92 (Oversize broadside))
    - Franco Gozzano, Galleria la Salita, 1970 (Box 93 (Broadside))
    - Pietro Cascella, arte Borgogna, undated (Box 93 (Broadside))
    - Vanni Viviani, il punto, Torino, 1971 (Box 93 (Broadside))
    - U. Mariani, galleria d'arte san Michele, Brescia, 1971 (Box 93 (Broadside))
    - L'ambiente spaziale di Lucio Fontana, galleria d'arte del Naviglio, Milano, 1971 (Box 94 (Broadside))
    - Man Ray, studio Marconi, Milano, 1974 (Box 94 (Broadside))
    - Gianni di Bernardi, galleria Apollinaire, Milano, 1966 (Box 94 (Broadside))
    - Addamiano, galleria d'arte Studio 188, Trani, 1970 (Box 94 (Broadside))
  - MEC-Art, 1970s-2000s
    Consists of examples of Bertini's MEC-Art, or mechanical art.
    - Examples of MEC-ART (originals), 1970s-2000s (Box 95)
  - Visual poetry, 1961-1965
    - 1961-1965 (Box 96 (Oversize))
    - 1961-1965 (Box 97 (Broadside))
  - Artwork, 1951-2006
    Organized in catalog number order.
    Artwork includes paintings and other works by Bertini, P. a. Benoit, Henri Chopin, Bernard Heidsieck, Jean-Clarence Lambert, Ben Vautier, and others.
    - 1) Gianni Bertini: All' ombra d'un passato, 1959 (Box 99)
    - 2) Pierre-André Benoit: Juillet 1962 à Anduze (Box 99)
    - 6) Gianni Bertini: Vie d'artiste, 2003-2006 (Box 99)
    - Part of 7) Gianni Bertini: Mes longues nuits, undated (Box 99)
    - 13) Gianni Bertini: Solfizie, 1958 (Box 99)
    - Part of 16) Pierre-André Benoit - G. Bertini: Eclatement, 1961 (Box 109)
    - 20) Jean Jacques Lévêque - Gianni Bertini: Stèle pour Adam de la Halle, undated (Box 100)
    - 23) Bernard Heidsieck - Gianni Bertini - P.A. Gette: B2 B3, 1964 (Box 101)
    - 24) Bernard Heidsieck - Gianni Bertini - P.A. Gette: B2 B3, undated (Box 101)
    - 25) Bernard Heidsieck - Gianni Bertini - P.A. Gette: B2 B3, undated (Box 101)
    - 26) Bernard Heidsieck: Manuscrit complet de Poème-Partition B2 B3 (Excorcisme), 1962 August-October (Box 101)
    - Part of 27) Jean-Clarence Lambert - Gianni Bertini: Les Folies Françaises, 1964-1966; 3 folders (Box 98 (Oversize))
      Artwork for Les Folies Françaises.
    - Part of 32) Théodore Koenig - Gianni Bertini: Etats d'imagination, undated (Box 109)
    - 33) Roberto Sanesi - Gianni Bertini: Giano, undated (Box 101)
    - 42) Gianni Bertini: Lingogravure originale, 1950 (Box 101)
    - 43) Archive de la revue MEC, 1969-1971 (Box 102)
    - Part of 49) Geiger: Antologia di testi sperimentali, 1967 (Box 109)
    - 51) Jochen Gerz: Oeuvre conceptuelle, circa 1970-1971 (Box 103)
    - 52) Marcel Janco: Catalogue de mes sculptures, circa 1957 (Box 103)
    - Part of 61) Jean-Clarence Lambert: Le principe d'incertitude, 1965 (Box 109)
    - Part of 62) Stelio Maria Martini: Schemi, undated (Box 109)
    - 65) Jean-Claude Moineau: Exposition-manifeste sur le Meta-Art, 1969 (Box 103)
    - 66) Ito Motoyuki: The ear festival, undated (Box 103)
    - 70) Salvadore Passarella: Paese indio, 1974 (Box 103)
    - 72) Vittorio del Piano: No didendiamo la nostra libertà!, 1974 (Box 103)
    - 76) Jiri Valoch: Ensemble d'oeuvres, circa 1970-1972 (Box 103)
    - Part of 78) Henri Chopin: Enluminure, undated (Box 109)
    - 83) Henri Chopin dans l'Essex, 1972 (Box 103)
    - 84) Henri Chopin: Lettre manuscrite, undated (Box 103)
    - 85) Henri Chopin: The Paddoocks - cul de sac, undated (Box 103)
    - 93) Alvermann et Gaul: Questionnaire sur l'art moderne, 1963 (Box 104)
    - 94) Alain Roussel: Résultat d'une enquête, undated (Box 104)
    - 95) Mai 1968 - Manifeste sous forme d'idéogrammes (Box 104)
    - 96) Adriano Spatola: Aviazone / Aviatore, undated (Box 104)
    - 97) Ensemble de catalogues d'invitation, undated (Box 104)
    - 98) Photographie originale, 1951 (Box 104)
    - 99) Joyce Mansour: Invitation pour la sortie de Ca, 1970 (Box 104)
    - 100) Alighiero Boetti: Manifesto 1967 (Box 104)
    - 101) Ben Vautier: Invitation au Festival Non Art, 1969 (Box 104)
    - 102) Ben Vautier: Invitation pour son exposition, 1970 (Box 104)
    - 103) Ben Vautier: Carton d'invitation, 1970 (Box 104)
    - 104) René de Solier: Invitation pour le bal costumé "l'Insolite est de rigueur", 1963 (Box 104)
    - 105) Jürgen Claus: Conférence sur la "strutture sottomarine", 1970 (Box 104)
    - 106) Enrico Baj: Invitation sous forme de carte postale originale détournée, 1965 (Box 104)
    - 107) Jakubik - Kordos - Mlynarcik - Mudroch: Mail Art, 1970-1971 (Box 104)
    - 108) Shimizu Toshihiko: 2 photographies en noir et blanc originales, undated (Box 104)
    - 109) Bertini - Mariani - Rotella: Affiche pour leur exposition commune, 1969 (Box 104)
    - 110) Rodolfo Arico: Affiche sur papier creponne, 1969 (Box 104)
    - 111) Poesia visiva internazionale: Catalogue de l'exposition, 1972 (Box 104)
    - 112) Daniel Spoerri: Invitation sur papier en-tête du Nouveau Réalisme, 1970 (Box 104)
    - 113) Timm Ulrichs: Kunst-diebstahl als totalkunst-demonstration, 1971 (Box 104)
    - 115) Cartons d'invitations sur papier cartonné de différentes couleurs, circa 1969-1980 (Box 105)
    - 116) Journal d'exposition année 1 numéro 1, 1963 (Box 105)
    - 117) Deschamps: Exposition Le rose de la vie. 1964 (Box 105)
    - 118) L. Fontana: Manifesto Blanco, undated (Box 105)
    - 119) Alain Jacquet, 1967 October 13 (Box 105)
    - 120) Tino Stefanoni, 1968 February 2 (Box 105)
    - 121) Gianni Pisani, 1968 May 1 (Box 105)
    - 122) Thomas Bayrle, 1968 March 29 (Box 105)
    - 123) Daniel Buren, 1968 October 23 (Box 105)
    - 124) Contenotte, 1968 November 20 (Box 105)
    - 125) Mario Nanni, 1969 January 31 (Box 105)
    - 126) Erik Dietmann, 1969 February 25 (Box 105)
    - 127) François Arnal, 1969 March 26 (Box 105)
    - 128) Elio Marchegiani, 1969 April 29 (Box 105)
    - 129) Bocola-Dané-Fiori-Mazzorati-Raffaela, 1969 October 14 (Box 105)
    - 130) Willy Orskov, 1969 November 12 (Box 105)
    - 131) Tino Stefanoni, 1969 November 28 (Box 105)
    - 132) Luca Patella, 1970 May 4 (Box 105)
    - 133) Télémaque: Exposition le 7 nov 1967 (Box 106)
    - 134) Sue Bitney: Exposition le 26 septembre 1968 (Box 106)
    - 135) Richard Hamilton: Exposition novembre 1968 (Box 106)
    - 136) Arnaldo Pomodoro: Exposition le 26 avril 1968 (Box 106)
    - 137) Enrico Baj: Exposition le 6 février 1969 (Box 106)
    - 138) Lourdes Castro: Exposition le 27 mars 1969 (Box 106)
    - 139) Hsiao: Exposition le 22 avril 1969 (Box 106)
    - 140) Harold Persico: Exposition le 22 mai 1969 (Box 106)
    - 141) Maglione: Exposition le 28 mai 1969 (Box 106)
    - 142) Ceretti: Exposition le 19 juin 1969 (Box 106)
    - 143) Gerald Gooch: Exposition le 6 novembre 1969 (Box 106)
    - 144) Richard Hamilton: Exposition le 4 décembre 1969 (Box 106)
    - 145) Keiso: Exposition le 14 mai 1970 (Box 106)
    - 146) Enrico Baj: Exposition le 2 décembre 1971 (Box 106)
    - 147) Carl Fredrik Reutersward: Exposition le 11 juin 1975 (Box 106)
    - 148) Tilson: Exposition le 23 juin 1975 (Box 106)
    - 149) Célèbre Tract de Pierre Restany, 1965 (Box 107)
    - 150) Exposition Niki de Saint-Phalle: Feu à volonté, 1961 (Box 107)
    - 151) Exposition Bertini: Le pays réel, 1962 (Box 107)
    - 152) Exposition Rotella: Cinecittà, 1962 (Box 107)
    - 153) Exposition Christo: Le rideau de fer, 1962 (Box 107)
    - 154) Exposition Foldès, 1962 (Box 107)
    - 155) Restarant de la Galerie J, 1963 (Box 107)
    - 156) Affiche de l'exposition "Bertinisations suite", 1965 (Box 107)
    - 157) Boris Vansier: 30 portraits du Général de Gaulle, 1965 (Box 107)
    - 158) Harold Stevenson: Soirée unique, 1965 (Box 107)
    - 159) Uriburu: Performance "Marie-Antoinette et les favorites de France", 1967 (Box 107)
    - 160) Iris Clert et Pierre Cardin: Invitation et carte de membre, undated (Box 107)
    - 161) M. Goeritz: Tract sur papier jaune, 1960 (Box 107)
    - 162) Edouard Jaguer: Tir de barrage, 1960 (Box 107)
    - 163) Ensemble de documents autour du movement Phases, circa 1958-1963 (Box 107)
    - 165) Robert Filliou, undated (Box 107)
    - 166) Pierre-André Benoit: Lettre autographe, 1967 (Box 107)
    - 167) Gianni Bertini: Carton d'invitation, 1960 (Box 107)
    - 168) Gianni Bertini: Exposition Le Pays Réel, undated (Box 107)
    - 169) Affiche sur papier fort de l'exposition conjointe Bertini et Harloff, 1966 (Box 108)
    - 170) Affiche pour l'exposition Schifano à la Galleria Stefanoni Lecco, undated (Box 108)
    - 171) Milanesi - Perotti - Sarenco, 1968 (Box 108)
    - 172) Circo poetico, 1976 (Box 108)
    - 173) Rassegna del cinema independente, 1976 (Box 108)
    - 181) Lettera amorosa, 1963 (Box 107)
    - 182) Romanzo d'amore, 1966 (Box 107)
    - 183) Gianni Bertini: Galerie J, 1962 (Box 98 (Oversize))
  - Electronic media, undated; 1 (Box 110)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- August 2012 Acquisition, 1947-1951; 0.25; (1 box)
  Purchased from Derbylius Libreria Galleria di Carla Roncato on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
  - Transcribed correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 111)
- September 2013 Acquisitions, 1947-1996; 6.25; (4 boxes)
  Purchased from John Benjamins Antiquariat b.v. and Phillipe Luiggi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund
  - "Mostra di pittura Italiana contemporanea," annotated catalog, 2 volumes, 1947 July-August (Box 112)
  - Passport photographs, annotated on reverse, circa 1980s (Box 112)
  - Annotated photographs of paintings, from the "Nuclear Art" period, circa 1947-1949 (Box 112)
  - P.A. Benoit: Mail art addressed to Gianni Bertini, undated (Box 112)
  - Unpublished manuscripts of Gianni Bertini, 8 books, 1954 August - 1959 (Box 112)
  - "Project manuscrit d'un diplome lors d'un diner ace ses amis peintres en 1957," drawing on paper, 1957 October 16 (Box 113 (Oversize))
  - "La peinture n'est pa un faux-nez," collage, undated (Box 114)
  - "Bonne nouvelle année," painting on cardboard box, 1996 (Box 115 (Oversize))
- January 2016 Acquisition, 1952-1967; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Purchased from Philippe Luigi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
  - Writings, book art maquettes, and correspondence relating to Gianni Bertini and Henri Chopin, 1952-1967 (Box 116)
  - "Il Burchiello," book art box, containing a 45 RPM record, "Il Burchiello Sonetti recitati da Gianni Bertini", undated (Box 117)
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.